# **Federico Milana**

PhD candidate in Human-Al Interaction with a background in Computer Science and Human-Computer Interaction and expertise in machine learning, interpretability, and user-centered design. Experienced in developing Al applications to evaluate perception and user experience of Al in user studies.

Flat 12, Tounson Court Montaigne Close, Regency Street London, United Kingdom, SW1P 4AQ +44 779 9715 965

#### federicomilana@outlook.com

https://linkedin.com/in/fmilana in https://github.com/fmilana

#### **AWARDS**

# **UCL Faculty of Brain Sciences** 2018/2019 Dean's List

August 2019

Academic performance equivalent to top 5% student achievement.

# **Research Assistant** / University College London Interaction Centre

PhD Candidate / University College London Interaction Centre

August 2019 - November 2019

September 2020 - November 2024

Research on the effects of user interface design on user trust and autonomy delegation to chatbots.

Research on Human-Al Interaction, implementing gradient boosting, large language models and

interpretability techniques in text classification to evaluate non-expert interaction and perception of

#### **EDUCATION**

**EXPERIENCE** 

machine learning.

# Human-Computer Interaction MSc / University College London

September 2018 - August 2019

Graduated with Distinction.

## Computer Science BSc / King's College London

September 2015 - August 2018

Graduated with First-class honors and a specialization in Software Engineering.

# **VOLUNTEERING**

# **Reviewer for CHI 2024**

Honolulu, Hawaii

### **Reviewer for IMWUT 2024**

Melbourne. Australia

#### **Student Volunteer for CHI 2023**

Hamburg, Germany

#### **PUBLICATIONS**

# **Understanding Interaction with Machine Learning through a Thematic** Analysis Coding Assistant: A User Study / CSCW '25:

Computer Supported Cooperative Work and Social Computing / Forthcoming publication

Exploring how an Interactive ML tool facilitates critical reflection, new insights, and adaptation in analytical processes while uncovering misconceptions about ML in non-expert users.

# Chatbots as Advisers: the Effects of Response Variability and Reply **Suggestion Buttons** / CUI '23: Proceedings of the 5<sup>th</sup> International Conference on

Conversational User Interfaces / https://doi.org/10.1145/3571884.3597132

19 July 2023

Demonstrating how response variability and reply suggestion buttons significantly increase chatbot advice following.

# **SKILLS**

Machine Learning

**User Studies** 

Experimental Design

Interpretability

LLMs

**XGBoost** 

Python

scikit-learn

numpy

pandas

#### **PROJECTS**

#### Interpretable Text Classification / https://github.com/fmilana/explanations

January 2024 - August 2024

Implementing and evaluating LIME, SHAP, and transformers-interpret heatmaps for text classification using XGBoost and BERT in user studies.

# Thematic Analysis Coding Assistant / https://github.com/fmilana/tacodingassistant

September 2020 - January 2024

A desktop application implementing XGBoost to assist the qualitative coding phase of thematic analysis.

#### Social Trading Chatbot Advisor / https://github.com/fmilana/socialtradingchatbot

April 2019 - November 2019

A simulated social trading environment web application used in online experiments to measure user trust in conversational agents.